So we will continue looking at the reinforcement
the full reinforcement learning problem so
we left off where we defined a Markov decision
process right and so today's class will probably
be a short one okay because the next thing
next topic I need to start requires me to
define a lot of notations and stuff like that
so if I start that today I will probably end
up just defining the notation today and then
when I start again next week I will ask you
to I will have to ask you to recall the notation
and stuff like that or spend time writing
it out again so I will not do it.
So if I finish whatever I want to before the
proofs start right I will just stop today
so I will not start the notations okay so
let us see how it goes so right.
So we started looking at Markov decision process
last time so we said that it is specified
by set of states, actions right, transition
probabilities and right and possibly a gamma
so if you look at the RL textbook right they
leave out the gamma right if you look at any
OR textbook where also MDPs are used widely
right they would have the gamma in there right
so for them gamma is a very inherent part
of the problem but in the RL books you would
see that they would leave out the gamma even
though I mean gamma is inherent part of the
problem and somehow they just do not acknowledge
the fact that gamma changes the solution right
explicitly in the problem definition itself
so this is essentially what an MDP is all
about so what I will do is walk through one
of the examples from the textbook right.
So I am sticking to the textbook example so
that you can go back and read the book and
also because it is kind of makes the course
more related to the minor guys here okay,
so let us take the example of a recycling
robot from the book so how many of you have
been reading the book okay the number went
up by two since last time okay good So do
you remember the recycling robot yeah so what
was the thing about hmm okay hmm hmm ah haan
okay hmm so it is interesting did they just
turn on the mike or something anyway it is
interesting that you used the description
states okay so people heard him so I will
repeat it since I seem to have the louder
mike so you know that those things can also
pick up but I seem to have the louder mike
so let me repeat it so there is this robot
okay that has been created for the express
purpose of Swachh Bharat okay so it goes around
the building and finds all the empty cans
and gathers it and puts it in some kind of
a you know trash recovery system right recycling
system or whatever.
So for every can the bot gathers it is going
to get a reward of 1 right this is a number
I am pulling out of the hat right so let us
not talk about the reward now right so the
robot is supposed to gather cans that is essentially
what we wanted to do but being a robot it
is going to have a limited amount of power
that it can spend right it has a limited amount
of battery power that it can spend so it has
to choose carefully how it spends the battery
right it can go around looking for cans right
and if it is going to run out of battery then
it can do one of two things it can recharge
itself right.
Or it can just sit in a place like a trash
can and expect people to drop the empty cans
into that bot okay just sits in a place and
the people can just use it like a trash can
right so this is essentially the set up so
I have this bot that should I would like it
to go actively gather cans but I also do not
like it to run out of battery because if it
runs out of battery somebody has to go physically
either roll the robot or carry the lift the
robot and take it to a charging station and
charge it ok that is a very painful operation
so I really do not want it to run out of battery.
But then I do not want it to just sit idle
as as well because what it says is supposed
to do is gather cans right so how would you
model this problem so what are the states
and what are the actions what should be the
reward, the robot seems to be easy right so
well what do you want it to do you want it
gather cans so whenever it gathers can whenever
it gathers a can, you give it a reward right
so whenever it gathers a can you give it a
reward of plus 1 right so I am going to call
this r can plus 1 right then what you do not
want it to do you do not want it to run out
of battery.
Minus...it is just yeah something large right
so yeah so I would I would have preferred
to give it minus 10 or something but since
I am walking through the example in the book
okay so it is a minus 3 right so it is not
that bad I mean if we can collect 15 cans
and then die it is okay right so it is not
too it is not that bad I think so what else
if it charges if it chooses to charge right
so what happens do we give what do we do for
it do you give a positive reward or why does
no reward make sense it will give yeah just
the heck for heck of getting that reward it
will get recharged right but then recharging
is also good we want to convey the fact that
recharging also good.
So it is better than running out of battery
and if you recharge you have the potential
for getting more rewards in the future because
you go out and seek more cans right so that
way you have an indirect incentive for recharging
because in the future it allows you to do
something better right if you just look at
the immediate reward it looks like a bad thing
but if you think about it so in the future
you are making it more attractive for recharge
I mean if you look at the future outcomes
recharging is also very attractive okay.
What is below the threshold ..no no this is
not this is if you think about it this is
more to do with actions or something with
outcomes yeah battery levels hmm you could
you could make it all the more detailed you
can make it as detailed as you want right
now comes the crux how detailed do you want
to make the representation to be do you want
to make it a real number saying how much battery
charge I have you could get a continuous state
there right so what do you want to do you
want to do some kind of discretization right
so if I want to do a discretization so how
do I discretize ahh that brings us to another
question that completely we forgot to answer
that question what is the state?
The battery charge level should be the state
right and then anything else
the number of cans no let us just assume that
magically it takes a can and transports it
to yeah but that is an interesting if it has
a finite carrying capacity then you probably
need to throw in how many cans it has and
so before it has to make a trip to the dump
dumping ground or something like that so let
us assume for the time being it so as soon
as you put a can into that there is a teleporter
that takes it to the dumping ground okay.
Right or the bot has an infinite carry I am
just trying to make the problem simpler right
if you want to make the problem more and more
realistic right you will have to think about
a whole bunch of other things right for example
I am kind of making it at a very high level
I am not talking about the pose and I mean
the pose of the robot right the velocity with
which the bot is moving so all of these things
you need right if you want to actually going
to control the bot and then this assuming
all of those are somehow going to be magically
taken care of right.
So we are just assuming that you are only
worried about the charge of the bot right
yeah you had a question.. yeah we have been
talking about only discrete states and discrete
action so far we have not talked about continuous
states and continuous actions but you have
continuous state and continuous action MDP
okay, so the state is going to be the charge
right and possibly number of cans right and
other things but for the time being I am just
going to say I am not going to care about
all of that we will just look at charge just
to keep it a simple example right.
I am also keeping it in sync with the book
so and again so what do I do with charge I
can treat it as a number in which case I will
have to figure out how to handle a continuous
value right or I can start discretizing it
so how will I discretize it yeah so I again
well percentage is also not a discretization
unless you round it off okay.
So yeah so you could do something like that
or it could be even more aggressive right
I could do low medium high right and if you
really stop and think about it when would
you if I said if I do low medium high or something
like that when would I actually change my
decision about charging versus not charging
right only when I am low right so in some
sense you could even try operating with high
and low right or sufficient and low whatever
okay.
What is it?
Yeah great..actually I do not I am not having
my location at all here right so assuming
that there is always a convenient charging
point located nearby okay it is not like a
single base station I have to go there so
as soon as I find out okay I am running out
of charge right let us assume that as long
as the battery is low I can still get to a
charging point in fact I am going to assume
even something stronger so I could with some
probability keep operating even if my battery
is low right.
And I still not run out of assumption I make
is the following whenever I say recharge okay
I will have enough battery power to reach
the nearest recharge station and recharge
so after I pick the option to recharge I will
not run out of battery power, it is again
a very simplifying assumption right this makes
it easier for us to draw pictures as I will
do in a minute right but all the points that
are being raised are very good points right
so when you start trying to model a real system
right these are all calls that you will have
to make right.
So what is it that I would throw into my state
right what is it that I can ignore right and
so on so forth and yeah so Pallavi do you
remember the homework assignment we are asking
them yeah the third one we are asking them
we are giving them a word problem and asking
them to construct an MDP out of it right you
think so hmm..new assignment the third assignment
the one that was released today morning if
it was released yesterday then you are time
traveling okay released this morning.
Yeah so the new assignment and it is due on
Feb 14 yeah due on Feb 14th haan 14 which
is what Sunday yeah hmm hmm well plan ahead
if it is important to you finish on the 13th
or as it is more likely for lot of people
who have nothing to do 14th well you have
one more day, last question is that right
so there is a word problem you are expected
to construct an MDP, so you can think of similar
things but that is a more constrained word
problem so you will see that there is not
too many ways in which you can construct an
MDP out of it.
So but then the idea is that a lot of design
choices that you make when I give you a problem
specification right there are a lot of choices
that you make when you go from the problem
specification to an MDP right so when you
are talking about designing a reinforcement
learning solution for a problem the things
that you have to decide are the states, the
actions and the rewards these are the three
things that you have to decide and when you
are constructing an MDP additionally you will
have to figure out what this the transition
probabilities are also going to be because
without that you cannot solve the problem.
All right but in we are trying to use reinforcement
learning techniques to solve these problems
as we will see later on you do not need the
transition dynamics right you do not need
to explicitly model the transition dynamics
but you still need to make choices for states
actions and rewards so that is where we are
right now so after we finish this I will tell
you some simple way of constructing the transition
probability for the robot but that is fine
so essentially what I am going to do charge
is going to be now low or high okay.
And then what about actions, there is no pick
up let us say when I actively we find a can
I will automatically pick it up okay so I
will go so explore essentially or as they
say in the book actively seek cans because
explore is overloaded right so we have explore
exploit those kinds of things already so I
do not want to have an action called explore
okay, so you have you actively seek cans or
wait for cans or recharge right so is there
anything else that we need to define here
well yeah so I will tell you how we can get
around yeah that is a good point so maybe
you need a zero charge state.
But I will also tell you how to get around
that right so the assumption we are going
to make is if you run out of charge somebody
is going to take you and charge you right
then you are going to get this penalty of
minus three so what does that mean so from
low I can actually go to high with a penalty
of minus three ok so that is that is equivalent
to the zero charge state that you can make
it more complex so right now I am assuming
once you plug it in to charge I do not worry
about it until it is fully charged later right
see this is another thing which you with an
interesting point because I have discretized
it into low and high right.
So when will it run out of charge when it
when it will go from high to low state so
if it high is 100 percent high right it is
probably not going to go to the low state
when i take an action but if high is say 40
percent high almost surely as soon as I take
an action it is going to go into a low state
let us say 40 is the cutoff point right so
above 40 I say high below 40 I say low that
is percentage right for 40 percent I will
say high below 40 percent I will say low,
almost surely as soon as I take an action
it is going to go to low.
But then I am not making this distinction
I have made a discretization here right so
what will it look like to me and if I run
the robot multiple times what will it look
like to me sometimes it goes from high to
low sometimes it does not go from high to
low it stays in high so what is going to happen
here is I am going to translate this into
the probabilities of transition right so what
is the probability of going from high to low
right in fact if I you know if I knew all
about my the battery dynamics if I know how
much power each and every action takes and
if I am modeling this as a continuous valued
state there might not be any stochasticity
here.
Right I might be able to tell you very exactly
okay now at this point if this is the action
you are doing this is so much power that you
will consume and therefore the battery will
go from high to low all right so I might be
able to give that to you exactly so inherently
this might not be a stochastic system okay
I am only saying might not be because people
have worked with robots so you know that you
might specify as many initial conditions as
you want right the bot will do what it wants
to do right.
So it is still be a stochastic system but
it could potentially not be a stochastic system
if you know everything about the world right
but we are making it stochastic by virtue
of ignoring certain things that we could potentially
know about the system right and ignoring this
makes the system design a lot simpler maybe
we are giving up some things in terms of how
optimal our solutions can be but that is a
trade-off that you will often have to make
right so just the formulation itself is not
an easy task you have to think about it a
lot to figure out what would be the right
place to draw the line okay.
So these are the actions that we have to take
so I can actively seek cans, wait for cans,
recharge is there something else that we have
to specify so we have specified the states,
we have specified the actions we have specified
rewards for events right so if I collect a
can, I get a plus one right if I run out of
battery you get a minus three then if I recharge
you get 0, these are events that could happen
in the world right so these are so I have
to relate this to the states and actions only
then I can tell you what is the expected reward.
We will not talk about time at all right so
I told you for that at least for the initial
part of the course we will not talk about
time with how long it run say so what is it
that we need suppose I am actively seeking
cans what is the probability I will get a
reward of plus 1, if I am actively seeking
cans right what is the probability that I
will find a can correct right so I need to
still specify that if I am actively you are
if I am waiting for cans to come like what
is the probability that I will get a can what
is the derivative of what derivative of which
one?
Yeah yeah what is that, yeah why yeah maybe
may be not I do not know why you chose to
move from one to the other right I mean I
could have just stopped seeking because it
is running low on battery right so if I am
in some facility where people are just taking
cans and throwing them in the dustbin right
I might just happily go sit next to the can
dispensing place and act as a dustbin right
I will be happily getting rewards right I
might not even worry about recharging or anything
right.
So I might just choose to stop right so it
depends on that depends on the kind of environment
you are operating in right so even if I act
as a dustbin do I get enough cans then I might
not want to seek right so maybe there is some
time of the day maybe between 12 and 1.30
or something lot of cans will come if I just
go stand outside the cafeteria I do not have
to actively seek cans maybe after 1.30 I have
to go around seeking cans right I do not know
it depends on the system right.
I am not trying to be too overly realistic
here but I am just giving you what are the
factors that you have to take into account
right so if you start talking about what could
be optimal policies right then you are going
down a dangerous path that means you are going
to start designing your problem itself depending
on what you think the solution should be which
is a bad thing right you should put in all
the factors about the problem in the design
and then you should go and let the algorithm
figure out what the solution should be.
So you should not start thinking about what
the solution should be and then try to create
the rewards and the model itself I will give
you an example of that after I finish this
I will give an example of when that became
a problem okay so is it clear so now I need
to figure out if I actively seek ends what
is the probability that I will get cans right
is there anything else I need to know
yeah we will come to that.
Yeah it is related to that if I am actively
seeking cans what is the probability that
I will run out of battery because that also
determines my reward right or if I am waiting
for cans to come what is the probability I
will run out of battery may be 0 because I
have turned off everything and just waiting
for or maybe there is a leakage that is happening
yes a very small probability that I might
actually run out of battery right so.
So I need both of these to actually figure
out what will be the expected reward right
for a state action pair.
So I need to know what will be the expected
reward so I have to actually think about both
of these things if I am in a high state right
and I am actively seeking cans right so what
is the probability I will find a can does
it depend on whether I am in a high state
or not no right so if I am actively seeking
cans what is the probability I will get a
can okay so that is one thing I need likewise
if I am not actively seeking cans what is
the probability I will get a can that is second
thing you need on the other hand if I am in
a high state and actively seeking cans.
What is the probability I will run out of
battery there the state matters right and
likewise if I am in a low state and actively
seeking cans what is the probability I will
run out of battery there state matters likewise
for waiting for cans if I am in a high state
and I am waiting for a can yeah probability
of me running out of battery is very very
minuscule almost 0 but if I am in a low state
and waiting for a can so even with a leakage
power drawn I met actually run out of battery
so these are the things so you need to know
all of these right.
For time being I will say alpha is the probability
of you getting a can right and beta is the
probability of you getting a can if you are
waiting and then alpha is greater than beta
hopefully typically right we are talking about
probabilities I mean that might be momentarily
where beta is higher than alpha like I said
stand outside a cafeteria during lunch time
but then overall we are going to assume that
alpha is greater than beta since we have not
actually modeled the time of day anywhere
right we are just going to say alpha is greater
than beta right.
So now what else do we need yet we need to
define p right so for that what do we need
well if I am in state high what is the probability
I will go to state low okay forget about going
to out of battery that is what we needed for
the rewards but for the state transition so
from high to low what is the probability that
will happen if I am actively seeking a can
so that is basically what we need right so
I am in state high, I am actively seeking
a can what is the probability I will stay
in state high what is the probability will
go to state low.
Right so like that and likewise if I am in
state low and I am actively seeking a can
what is the probability I will stay in state
low what is the probability will go to state
high and I am in state low and I am waiting
for can what is the probability I will stay
in state low what is the probability I will
go to state high right and so on so forth
right so these are all the things that you
need for defining the state transition probabilities
okay of course if I am in state high and I
do action recharge what do we want?
Exactly.
So if I am in state low I do action recharge
with probability 1 I will go to state high
right so we will actually prohibit recharge
action in state High well it does not make
sense if I am already fully charged I do not
want to go plugging in again all right so
we will disallow that well it all depends
right I could just have a stochastic policy
I can say that ok my policy is that if I am
in state high with probability point 8 I will
search with probability point 2 I will just
stay so I mean so we are not talking about
solutions here.
I am just talking about defining the problem
this is what I was mentioning earlier also
do not do not get into how the solution will
look like right sometimes you will have to
think about how the solution will look like
because you need to know if you are giving
the state sufficient expressiveness so that
you know when the solution should change and
things like that but do not worry too much
about the structure of the solution.
So now we will just draw this some kind of
a state transition diagram.
Right so let us do the at state high right
so there are two actions from state high one
is actively seek cans right so active so what
are the possible outcomes of active ok so
what is the probability that I am going to
be in high some values equal is also possible
well it depends on how wide my high band is
rate and how much power my actor action is
going to consider I don't know this is to
say some numbers here right what is other
action I can take here
right and what is the
something some numbers it has now is there
anything else I need to specify I need to
look at what the reward is going to be for
having done that right.
So what will be the reward here what yeah
I will get plus one for a can but the expected
number of cans I am going to collect is alpha
right that is the probability of me getting
a can so the expected reward will be alpha
right likewise here the expected what is going
to be beta okay, so from low I have again
three actions no from low I have three actions
not two right I have three actions so what
are the actions right so I will do the easy
one first right from low if I do recharge
with probability 1 I will go to high and I
will get 0 reward right.
So now comes the more interesting case suppose
I do wait here is there any chance that I
will go to high I could right so that is also
possible but very low very low probability
because I am not doing anything so if I already
set point one here as the probability of discharging
I will say point 1 minus.. and I might still
get a can right and this one is
likewise if I am actively seeking does that
make sense right there is some small probability
I might not discharge and I will keep accruing
rewards at alpha right but then I might actually
discharge with a high probability and then
I go to the high state and I also get the
additional minus 3 along the way.
I mean whether you do this plus beta or plus
alpha or not is again a choice right you can
say that hey if I run out nobody is actually
going to give me a can right so people might
snatch away the can I already have I do not
know what you can choose whatever I mean this
is again a choice I just I just chose to add
the alpha and beta here you can choose not
to but you can you get the sense of what we
are doing here right so is a very very simple
problem it took us a while to identify all
the factors right and we chose to ignore a
whole bunch of factors because you identified
a lot of useful factors right we chose to
ignore a whole bunch of factors or in order
to come up with a simple tractable MDP right
great.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights reserved